The CIA is constantly pushing the the
envelope of legality
and they just wait for somebody to push
back. The reason why the Russians
haven't agreed to substantive talks
brokered by Donald Trump
is that they're winning.
So that it is now legal for the American
government to propagandize the American
people. Every one of them has seen
something. Some ship sometimes they're
coming out of the water. You know that I
probably shouldn't comment on.
Hello and welcome back to the channel.
I'm here today with John Kiriakou. Uh
quite well-known CIA whistleblower.
And I'd like to start today's interview
by welcoming John and asking him he
could give a quick introduction for
those who might not be familiar with his
work.
Sure. I'm John Kiriakou. I spent uh
almost 15 years at the CIA. I uh I was
the chief of the CIA's counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan after 9/11. I
blew the whistle on the CIA's torture
program in 2007, later went to the
private sector, and then after that was
the chief investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee.
Um now I'm a journalist, author
commentator
talk show host
bunch of different things.
How's what you're most well-known for
especially
in recent months on the internet it
seems is your initial whistleblowing
over the torture program or the enhanced
interrogation program as they called it.
It seems that this was the final straw
for you. Could you explain to people
what was occurring and why you thought
you had to speak out?
Yeah, the CIA had decided to torture its
prisoners after 9/11.
Plain and simple. And torture is
illegal. By any measure, it's illegal.
We have the Federal Torture Act of 1946.
We have the United Nations Convention
Against Torture.
The lawyers at the Justice Department
stood on their heads to somehow make it
not illegal. I disagreed with that and
decided to go public.
I work under Clive Stafford Smith. I
think I might have mentioned that. Um
and he sometimes talks about some of his
clients who are in Gitmo and some of the
um torture methods that were used on
them.
Do you find any of the methods used
particularly troubling?
Of the of the enhanced interrogation?
Yeah, most of them I found to be
particularly troubling.
Uh
in fact,
you know, rather than list these these
things, I'll tell you that
in 1946, we executed Japanese soldiers
who had waterboarded American prisoners
of war.
In
1968, we prosecuted successfully
prosecuted a soldier, an American
soldier, for waterboarding a North
Vietnamese prisoner. He was given 20
years in prison. So, this went from a
death penalty
uh
case
to 20 years in prison to all of a
sudden, like magic, just being suddenly
legal
in um
in 19 uh I'm sorry, in 2002. The the law
never changed.
We changed. And my position was if you
if you want to torture people,
that's on you, but you're going to have
to change the law because the law is
very clear.
Much of the
torture programs and the
these um wrongdoings were a response to
9/11 or at least they were framed that
way.
In how would you
say they should have responded to 9/11?
Oh, by hunting down those who had
perpetrated 9/11 and bringing them to
justice. And when I say justice, I don't
mean with a bullet to the head or with,
you know, a life without parole at
Guantanamo despite never having been
convicted of a crime. What you do is
what the Constitution tells you to do,
and that is to allow them to face a jury
of their peers
uh in a in a federal court.
If our contention was that the Al-Qaeda
leadership and Al-Qaeda fighters were
violating US law, then charge them with
a crime
and put them on trial.
It really was as simple as that.
It seems that
a lot of the things that happened within
the CIA are quite compartmentalized.
Do you think that in terms of individual
officers,
there wasn't a large awareness of of the
interrogation uh methods that were being
used?
>> There was not. When I When I was first
told about the uh the torture program,
uh there were fewer than two dozen
people in all of the entire American
government who knew about it.
Wow.
So so it seemed it was
from the top, really.
>> Oh, it came directly from the top, yes.
I want to ask a little bit about how you
feel
about the CIA now. Do you think that
this was a unique example of, I suppose,
incompetency, or do you think that they
generally have
issues like this across the board, many
of which the public may not be aware of?
Oh, yeah, it wasn't incompetency. In
fact, they were very competent in the
way they carried out a a torture
program. It was that the CIA is
constantly pushing the the envelope of
legality,
and they just wait for somebody to push
back. The problem is that the
congressional oversight committees,
which are supposed to be the bodies
that do push back, really act as little
more than cheerleaders for the CIA,
egging them on. Think of it this way.
The torture program
was created from the top of the CIA. The
director of the of the CIA, George
Tenet, ordered its creation.
But, it was authorized, and it was
funded by the congressional oversight
committees. So, these protestations
later that members of Congress had no
idea that this program was taking place,
that was just a lie.
They were just lying to their
constituents and to the American people.
Not only did they know that the torture
program was taking place, they had
authorized it,
and they had appropriated funds to fund
it.
I know you mentioned you've mentioned
before that even the president signed
off on some of the wrongdoing of the
CIA.
How much autonomy does the CIA have
though? Is it does it have power
above and over the presidency?
No.
>> Okay. Okay.
And and at the [clears throat] end of
the day, the president had signed off on
on everything that the CIA was doing.
They did nothing without executive
approval, nothing. Because they would
have just been prosecuted.
Mhm.
Back to I I briefly mentioned 9/11, and
I've heard um
you respond to this before, but where
were you on the day of 9/11, and and how
did you respond to that situation?
Yeah, I was at CIA headquarters. I had a
9:00 meeting planned with uh the
director of counterterrorism
at the White House. We were going to see
Condoleezza Rice, who was the national
security advisor.
And I got a call from the driver saying
that the car was ready to take us to the
White House.
Went up to his office to tell him it was
time to go
and saw on his secretary's television
that the World Trade Center one tower
was burning. I asked her what happened.
She told me a plane had flown into it.
And then the second plane flew into
tower one.
And then it started that that
nightmare that 25-year long nightmare
now just began as easy as easily as
that.
And what do you think fueled the
response to 9/11? Do you think it was
primarily fueled by fear or anger or
Yes and yes and a desire for revenge.
Yes.
This was the greatest intelligence
failure in the history of the republic.
And so, you know, 3,000 Americans lost
their lives that day. That one day
because we didn't do our jobs.
And so there was this great desire to
extract revenge.
Yes. Yes.
>> overwhelming.
You mentioned that it's
intelligence failure, a major
intelligence failure.
Do you also think that that was an
element um
an element of this can be attributed to
policy failure?
Absolutely.
You know, I I say all the time, too,
that it wasn't just an intelligence
failure. It was an American failure.
The CIA failed, obviously. The FBI also
failed because the FBI knew that the
hijackers were were loose in the United
States. The State Department failed
because none of those hijackers were
here illegally. They went through the
visa application process and they were
granted visas by the State Department.
Congress failed to to appropriate enough
counter-terrorism funding to really lock
the place down. It was It was a failure
across the board. You know, the Federal
Aviation Administration failed because
security at the airports wasn't
appropriate to the point where 19 people
boarded airplanes that day with box
cutters in their pockets. How in the
world did that happen?
And looking back, do you think that
there were
warning signs that were missed before
9/11? I mean, it's led to
millions of innocent people being killed
in Iraq and and other areas of the
Middle East. Do you think that there
were warning signs that should have been
noticed before 9/11 occurred? You know,
I'm not sure I would call it so much a
warning sign as as I would a deliberate
policy.
Um what what made these Al-Qaeda people
hate us so much that they just wanted to
carry out the wholesale slaughter of
Americans?
It was US foreign policy.
That's what they were objecting to.
And um
we've never undertaken a review of our
foreign foreign policy.
Back a little bit to your choice to come
out and
be a whistleblower. Um
in what ways were people like you and
others marginalized within the CIA? I
mean, I know you were later imprisoned.
But um were there other ways in which
you were marginalized?
No, when I resigned from the CIA, I was
at the very top of my game. I I resigned
because I got divorced and I wanted to
spend more time with my children.
So, I I was never marginalized. The last
job I had at headquarters was as the
executive assistant to the CIA's Deputy
Director for Operations.
So, I my my career was on a a rocket
ride to the top. Um
I I was never marginalized.
Okay.
So, would you mind going into a little
bit more detail on
when you spoke out and then later you
were investigated and subsequently
imprisoned? Could you explain
um these events?
Yeah, I I thought certainly that
somebody would go public with the CIA's
torture program
uh because there were so many people
internally who were opposed to it.
Opposed to the point where they were
resigning, they were curtailing their
positions and coming back from from the
secret prison site, and I thought
certainly somebody was going to say
something. And then nobody did. And then
finally in December of 2007 at the
urging of Brian Ross of ABC News,
I went public and said something. The
Bush administration investigated me for
a year from December of 2007 until
December of 2008 and then decided that I
had not committed a crime and then
closed the case.
Barack Obama became president a month
later.
John Brennan became his Deputy National
Security Advisor for Counterterrorism.
He asked the Attorney General to
secretly reopen the case against me.
They investigated me for three more
years and then charged me with five
felonies in uh January of 2012,
a little more than four years after I
had gone public.
And how long did you spend in prison?
23 months.
What was that experience like? I mean,
being
imprisoned for
essentially no real wrongdoing. How did
you deal with that situation? Well,
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> it's a difficult question to under to to
answer because
on the one hand you're in shock, you
can't believe this has happened. On the
other hand, you have to get a hold of
your bearings.
Um I wrote a book about the experience
that actually won two literary awards.
It's called Doing Time Like a Spy: How
the CIA Taught Me to Survive and Thrive
in Prison. And it's done well enough
that that the publisher uh just came out
with a second edition a month ago.
But um I decided that
I was trained for this.
That I was going to to use the life
lessons that the CIA taught me to keep
myself safe. And at the top of the
social heap, I would forge strategic
alliances in prison. And honestly, by
the end of it, I felt like I was
practically running the place.
Mhm.
Okay, that's interesting.
So you your your CIA skills helped you
be
I told myself I had lived and served in
far worse places than Loretto,
Pennsylvania.
And so I was going to just take the bull
by the horns and manage it. And that's
what I did.
You mentioned as well just a moment ago
that you were surprised others didn't
speak out about the enhanced
interrogation um methods.
I've also heard you in other interviews
discuss the fact that CIA officers may
have a
um certain personality type.
Could you explain whether it may be you
think that it's because of this
personality type that there was a lot of
silence and um complacency within the
program?
Well, yeah, what you're talking about is
is
the CIA's policy of hiring people who
have sociopathic tendencies. Not
sociopaths, but people who have
sociopathic tendencies are willing to
work in moral, legal, and ethical gray
areas. I think though that the reason
people who were even opposed to the
to the torture program didn't say
anything was not because they had
sociopathic tendencies, but because they
feared for their job security.
The One of my attorneys said something
to me that made perfect sense. He said,
"This case is so much bigger than John
Kiriakou. This case is about making an
example so that if anybody else in the
CIA is thinking about going public and
reporting wrongdoing,
they're going to see what happened to
you. You lost your pension, you lost
your freedom, you lost your family, you
lost everything.
Are people going to really want to take
that that risk?"
And the answer's no.
I suppose a lot of people might view
espionage as a way of protecting
national security.
Do you think that
it's more often than not, or at least in
a lot of cases, used merely to silence
embarrassment?
That That's a very good question.
Um
Yes.
I do, actually. There's a law in this
country, and this is why the Bush
administration declined to prosecute me.
There's a law that says that it is
illegal to classify a criminal act.
And torture, the FBI said, was a
criminal act.
And so, you can't prosecute me because I
revealed a crime.
Mhm.
Well, the Obama administration said it
wasn't torture,
and thus it wasn't a criminal act. And
so, my revelations
were violations of of Espionage Act.
They ended up dropping all the espionage
charges against me. I hadn't committed
espionage, and they knew it.
But, um
But, yeah, to answer your question, I
think
I think a lot of what we see coming out
of the CIA in terms of classification
um is is an effort just to
protect the agency. Sure.
And after these experiences, after your
time in the CIA, and then subsequently
um your treatment
do you are you rather cynical towards
the powers that be or or
>> I am.
It's been my considered experience
my personal experience
that most of our leaders are lying.
Right? They don't have any interest at
all in in
exposing the truth or perpetuating
truths.
Mhm. Um they see their job as um
carrying out the policies of whomever
happens to be in the White House and
doing so clandestinely, and doing so
despite the fact that it may, you know,
be vi- a violation of the law.
And anyone who tries to stand in their
way should be destroyed.
That's really what the bottom line is.
Mhm.
And it's interesting because
the UK
the US, they claim to be um democracies.
Right.
And do uh that's an interesting point as
well that links on from this is
whether the CIA in its activities um
that the public aren't made aware of is
undermining democracy. What what would
you say?
>> I I would go even even further than
that. The the
the British government is even tougher
on whistleblowers than the American
government is. We don't have an Official
secrets act, like you do.
And we don't have a terrorism act, like
you do. So, if I if I were, you know, in
the UK, and I said that I support
Palestinian human rights, I could be
prosecuted just for saying that.
I could be stopped at the airport and
told that while I'm not under arrest,
I'm also not free to go. I have three
friends,
one of whom is a former British
ambassador,
who have been stopped at the airport and
threatened with
with um arrest under the terrorism act
or the uh official secrets act. It's
draconian in the UK. At least in the US,
you have a fighting chance with the
Espionage Act. Not so in the UK. It's
much tougher.
I mean, we've seen this as well with the
terrorism acts. Um
recently with with a certain protest
group in alignment with Palestine and
Right.
>> designating them as a terrorist
terrorist group um
to then arrest
harmless protesters in the street. So, I
suppose
there's issues with
Yeah, and in the United States, there
are individual states that are trying to
enact similar legislation or legislation
that is similar to what the the UK um
has. In the state of Florida now, and
this won't last very long because it'll
be it'll be successfully challenged in
the courts, but it is illegal
to go onto a social media platform and
um and express support for Palestinians.
Uh to the point where I happened to be
in Miami 2 weeks ago,
and a woman wrote on Facebook that she
supported uh
Palestinian human rights.
And sure enough, the Miami police
knocked on her door the next day and
demanded that she explain herself.
She closed the door and they walked
away. They didn't arrest her, but when
an arrest comes, and it will,
uh that law is going to be thrown out.
So, there is this move in support of
of
you know, squelching free speech
and any challenges to to Israel at all.
It's as though, you know, Benjamin
Netanyahu is president of the United
States right now.
I'd like to um go to a slightly
different well, a very different topic,
which is um
the idea of targeted killings or
assassinations carried out by the
CIA. Um
could you explain the dynamics of these
um
activities and how the CIA behaves in
these areas?
Yeah, uh the CIA has a um
has a unit
Actually, there there are several units
whose job it is to simply travel around
the world as needed and carry out
assassinations.
Uh
if if the president
deems a person to be what is called a
clear and present danger
to the United States,
to
American citizens or American
installations,
they can be killed according to US law.
And so, these teams
fan out each week.
They carry out their assassinations, and
then the next week they get the next
list of names, and then just do the same
thing week after week after week.
I suppose the obvious question um how is
this not possible to answer um
with any certainty, but
are there
regular cases of wrongful executions, I
suppose? Cases where people are killed
I would I would say there have to be.
There There would have to be.
Keep in mind, none of these people have
ever been charged with a crime.
So, we don't even know
what it is they're supposed to have
done.
Um and I will add that since the Obama
administration,
the position of the
Justice Department has been that the
president has the legal authority
to order the assassinations of American
citizens
who have never been charged with a
crime.
If the president decides that this
person is dangerous,
the president can legally order that
that person be assassinated.
Purely out of interest, do you know if a
similar program exists in the UK?
No idea. Okay. Okay.
But you know what? If it did, it would
be
so highly classified that almost nobody
would know about it.
My guess is that there is no similar
program. And And I'll tell you what I
base that on. I'm I'm friendly with a
handful of retired MI6 officers.
And they have told me independently of
one another how disappointed they were
in the United States after 9/11 because
the CIA just started killing everybody.
And that's something that MI6 just
wasn't doing.
Mhm.
But I think um possibly
there's a common um
occurrence where people who aren't from
the United States underestimate the
impact that 9/11 had on people,
especially in New York, and and
Without a doubt.
Yes.
Okay. Well, I want to move on a little
bit again to some geopolitics.
Um
particularly the Russia-Ukraine war.
So Today's the fourth anniversary.
Yes, but it seems to be um
never-ending. It doesn't seem like
there's too much of a um working towards
peace. But um how do you view the war
and NATO's role in perhaps poking the
bear?
Um
how do you view this situation and how
the war came about?
I believe the war really originated in
2014.
Uh not in 2022.
Uh you know, the United States had
repeatedly promised
the Russians that NATO would not expand
to Russia's borders.
And then we did exactly that. We
expanded right up to Russia's borders.
And we promised the Russians repeatedly
that Ukraine would not become a part of
NATO. And then we announced that we were
going to start talks with Ukraine to
become a part of NATO.
So we lied repeatedly to the Russians.
The Russians twice asked to join NATO
themselves.
And twice, under President Bill Clinton
and under [clears throat] President
Barack Obama, we told the Russians that
was not going to happen.
Can you imagine how different the world
would be today
if the Russians were part of NATO?
Well, in 2014,
we deposed
a prime minister, a a democratically
elected prime minister of Ukraine, who
happened to be pro-Russian. And we
replaced him with
a pro-American, pro-Western prime
minister. The Russians saw this as a
direct challenge. And so they snatched
Crimea. For their own protection, they
snatched Crimea.
Uh and then
elected
and said that he wanted to not only
uh
begin accession talks
for Ukraine to become a member of the
European Union, he announced publicly
that he wanted to join NATO.
And the Russians had had enough. And the
reason why this thing is still dragging
on, the reason why the Russians haven't
agreed to substantive talks brokered by
Donald Trump
is that they're winning.
And there's no reason for them to engage
in talks because they're winning.
The bottom line is that
Ukraine at the end of this is going to
be a rump state.
It might even be a landlocked state.
And it will never be in NATO.
But the Russians are trying to put as
much hurt on the Ukrainians as they
possibly can.
And there's nothing that the United
States or NATO can do to stop them.
So, why do you think it almost seems as
if um NATO and the United States and
these Western countries wanted to cause
a conflict um
such as the conflict that's now
occurring. Why is it in their interest
to have this conflict going on at the
moment? Because a weak Russia is always
in the national interests of the Western
countries.
Just like a bankrupt China would be in
the national interest of, you know, the
United States and the Western countries.
Because if you keep Russia weak, that
makes the European Union and NATO and
the United States strong. It really is
that simple.
And do you view, I mean, in the UK the
media is incredibly um biased, the
mainstream media.
Do you think that Russia are as much of
a threat as the media makes out or a
threat at all to the West.
Yeah, I I don't have rose-colored
glasses.
Um I think that sure, the Russians are
going to be a threat. Um
yes, the Russians kill their political
opponents
uh whether domestically or overseas.
We've seen that play out in the UK.
We've seen it play out all across
Russia.
Um but at the same time,
I don't believe that the Russians are an
existential threat to the West. I really
don't. I think that Russia has been very
badly mishandled
by especially the US and the UK.
And we have missed several opportunities
to bring Russia into the Western fold.
And now Russia will never be in the
Western fold.
We're going to be in a state of war with
Russia for a very long time. Even if
it's not a hot war. Even if it's another
Cold War, which is a shame because I
think that when the Soviet Union fell
apart,
we really did have an opportunity to
change the global landscape. And we just
let it go.
Another country that the West um
often vilifies is China. You just
mentioned. Um
How do you view China as a international
threat? I We've recently had um
the Chinese Embassy
controversy.
Um how do you view that in particular
and also China's broader
influence and role?
Yeah, China In my view, China really is
the threat to the West. Not because the
Chinese are bad people,
but because the Chinese economy is so
strong
and the Chinese are so flush with cash
that they've essentially been able to
buy friends all around the world.
You know, there's this ongoing joke here
in the United States. Why can't we have
nice roads and nice airports and nice
bridges and nice hospitals and bullet
trains?
How come the Chinese have all those
things? Well, it's because we spend a
trillion dollars a year on weapons and
the Chinese don't.
I I spoke with a Congolese diplomat one
time and he made a statement that was so
simple and so powerful. He said, "You
promise us democracy. The Chinese
promise us food."
There's a big difference. You can't eat
democracy.
Yeah.
>> So, the only thing that has saved us, I
think, so far is the Chinese through
history have not really been
an imperialist
expansionist country.
We can have a conversation about Tibet.
Mhm.
But, Tibet aside,
uh the Chinese don't normally invade
other countries. You know, certainly we
fought the Chinese in in Korea.
Uh they have had border skirmishes with
the Indians and with the Vietnamese.
But, the Chinese don't actively invade
other countries like the United States
does. The Chinese have one foreign
military
Ironically, they share with the United
States
in uh Djibouti in the Horn of Africa.
The Chinese, as enormous as the Chinese
government and military are, they have
one aircraft carrier. One. We have 24
aircraft carriers. Now, half of them are
not seaworthy, but we have a lot more
aircraft carriers than the Chinese do.
Mhm.
>> And so, I'm I'm not worried about
Chinese military expansion so much as
I'm worried about Chinese economic
expansion. There's a There's a satirical
newspaper here in the United States
called The Onion.
And they had a headline last week, and
the headline was Chinese content to sit
back and watch US destroy itself.
And the reason why that's funny is that
it's true. Yes. Yeah.
So they're not not the military threat
that other nations perhaps throughout
history have been, but that they've got
the ability to dominate economically.
Yes. Yes, indeed.
>> Okay. Okay. Well, before moving on to
the last of the sort of geopolitical
issues, which I'm sure you can guess
what what that will be. Um
I've got a few broader questions about
media and narrative.
Um
So
often the UK at least seems to portray
Russia and China and these
Eastern countries as um
purveying disinformation, and
disinformation being a primarily foreign
uh thing. Do you think that
with tools if we think that the UK and
other Western countries aren't also
engaged in similar disinformation? Oh,
yeah. Of course we're engaged in similar
disinformation to the point where here
in the United States, during the Obama
administration in 2014,
we changed the law
so that it is now legal for the American
government to propagandize the American
people.
So of course we're out there engaging in
disinformation.
Without any question.
Uh do you think that journalists Well,
do you know if journalists are used as
instruments in intelligence battles or
used by intelligence agencies? Without
any question. And we know that thanks to
the Freedom of Information Act. We know
that the CIA will threaten journalists
with cutting off their access, not
inviting them to the CIA Christmas party
anymore, threatening them if they
publish certain articles. There are
major
major American journalists at the
biggest outlets in the country
who will send their articles to the CIA
for clearance before they send them to
their own editors.
So yeah, I feel like the CIA has a
stranglehold on on intelligence
reporting here in the United States.
And I would assume you think that that's
very problematic.
Oh, yeah.
Part of the problem is that is that
American outlets, news outlets,
especially in print journalism, just
simply no longer have budgets for
investigative journalism. And you know,
where you have the likes of the
Washington Post and the New York Times
that literally brought down a president
in Richard Nixon,
they now just don't have investigative
journalism.
Mhm.
Okay.
I mean,
I think we could spend more time on that
topic, but I think the the Israel issue
is going to be a big one as well, so
I'll move on to that. Um firstly, I'll
ask you about the genocide or or I don't
know if you um
recognize it as a genocide, but Israel's
military actions. Um Yeah, it's a
genocide, all right, by any definition.
Mhm.
So,
what do you feel about the situation
that's occurring in Israel and Gaza and
even after the ceasefire, um the deaths
that have been occurring and and the
civilian and military casualty
proportions, how do you feel about this
situation and why do you think that the
West and particularly the US is so
complacent in their response? Um I I I
feel that this is a genocide. I think
it's very clear that it's a genocide. It
meets every definition of a genocide,
including ethnic cleansing.
Um
I don't believe there has been a
ceasefire because the Israelis have
continued to kill Palestinian civilians
quite literally every single day since
the so-called ceasefire
was initiated.
And um
And
I think the reason why the United States
You know, I hesitate to use the word
complacent because
complacency implies disinterest.
I'm going to say
I think the reason why the US is
a part of this and it's on the side of
of the Israelis and Israeli actions in
both Gaza and the West Bank is that
the pro-Israel lobby in the United
States is so strong
that almost no one has the guts
to stand up to Israel.
You know, there are Israeli lobbyists in
literally every single one of the 535
um members of Congress.
On Capitol Hill, there are Israeli
lobbyists in literally every single one
of the 50 state legislatures. And now we
have Israeli lobbyists lobbying at the
um at the local level.
Why?
Why do Israelis care
about the outcome of American school
board races?
Or who gets elected mayor of what town?
Or who gets elected to some little teeny
tiny district in Kansas
or Arizona?
It doesn't make sense to me.
Unless it's a concerted effort to
control American foreign policy.
Which I I believe that it is.
Do you think that
um
the attacks on Iran for example are uh
proof of um
the fact that Israeli influences APAC or
the lobbyists groups might want to
control American policy. Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Iran is not a threat to the United
States, period. I state that as fact.
States. The Iranians don't have weapons
to attack the United States, and even if
they had weapons, they don't have
delivery systems to attack the United
States. They're a threat to Israel. Why?
Because Israel's a threat to them.
Somebody said something to me the other
day, and it was so simple and it made
such sense.
Why are we not talking about North Korea
right now? I can tell you why. Because
North Korea has a nuclear weapon.
So, nobody's going to attack North Korea
because they don't want North Korea to
attack them. That's why the Iranians
have sought a nuclear weapon. Well, I
mean, the CIA says that they actually
haven't sought a nuclear weapon, but
were they to seek one,
it's to protect themselves
against the Israelis. The Israelis who
have dozens, apparently,
dozens of nuclear weapons.
And in terms of the intelligence
corporation between the US and Israel,
how how deep does this go?
You know, that I probably shouldn't
comment on.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah.
Um
So, I
if this is something you can't comment
on as well, then I can um cut it from
the interview or whatever, but in in the
case of October the 7th,
do you see it
as an intelligence breakdown or complete
political complacency or something else?
I mean, I know we have the Hannibal
directive, but what what would you say
about this? I I'm of two minds about
October 7th. On the one hand,
it was clear for two or three weeks in
advance of the attack that something was
a foot. There were settlers who were
warning Jerusalem that an attack was
coming. But these two morons, ministers
Ben-Gvir and
and Smotrich,
who are in charge of security,
apparently believed, say they believed,
that the attack was going to come in the
West Bank, not in Gaza. And that's why
they were unprepared. That's one side of
the story.
The other side, and I think there's
probably something to this,
was
this attack on October 7th gave the
Israeli government the green light to
utterly destroy Gaza.
Destroy it. There are probably 200,000
people dead.
Officially, there are 69,000. We have no
idea how many dead remain under the
rubble, just as skeletons now.
But I think that was the whole plan was
to completely destroy Gaza
and to throw out literally all of the
Palestinians so that the whole area
could be resettled
with with
Israelis.
And do you think there's any way of
um
Hamas and the Israeli government coming
to a uh
proper effective ceasefire or a peace
plan or a two-state solution, or do you
think that the Israelis just aren't
interested in that?
>> No, Benjamin Netanyahu very proudly said
that he killed the two-state solution.
There is no two-state solution.
It's gone.
And it's gone because he killed it.
So, no.
Hamas is, you know, a handful of guys
with long beards.
Uh the Israelis are murdering civilians,
women, children, the elderly, the sick.
And you can't have as a viable policy to
just kill everybody. The Israelis of all
people in the world should know
something like that.
Um and so
I I don't think there's any chance of a
of a true ceasefire. I don't think
there's any chance of of a real peace.
Look, when the Israelis continue to bomb
uh the Palestinian negotiating team
while they're in other countries,
there won't be any peace. No. Mhm.
And do you think in terms of the
political influence that um
Israel has in the US, do you think that
there's any way to mitigate this or try
and reverse this or do you think it's
just too embedded into every area area
of US politics?
>> it's a combination of being embedded and
and also of senior policy makers not
having any problem with it. Donald Trump
has no problem with the Israelis running
US foreign policy. And Joe Biden also
didn't have a problem with that.
Mhm. No. And and Barack Obama and George
W. Bush and they all just accept that
that Benjamin Netanyahu is going to run
American foreign policy.
I mean, I I think this will lead on to
some of my um
next questions, but do you think that
there's a reason for this beyond
the common claim that Israel is our
greatest ally and Israel is a point of
strength in the Middle East? Sure, it's
money. It's money.
If If you are not 1,000% pro-Israeli,
if you are not an ardent Zionist, they
will spend millions of dollars to defeat
you in an election.
And more often than not, they're
successful.
So, if you have any hopes for a
political career in the United States,
you have to be ardently and publicly
Zionist.
Okay. Okay. And I'm going to move on now
to some um
points of controversy, some points of
recent controversy. Um first, the
Epstein files. I I saw you discuss this
in a podcast that was released um 3 days
ago.
In terms of Epstein himself, I've heard
you say that you think or know or think
certainly that he was murdered. Um
Can you explain?
>> I've been adamant from the beginning I
do not think he was murdered. Oh, okay.
Okay.
>> I believe he committed suicide.
And in terms of him being the claims
that are increasingly emerging about him
being an intelligence asset, um what are
your
>> That's another thing that I've been very
consistent over. I have said from the
very beginning that I believed he was an
Israeli access agent, and that's been
borne out.
And not only was he an Israeli access
agent, he appears to have
at least volunteered
to work with CIA,
FBI, MI5, MI6, the Germans. He reached
out repeatedly to the Russians.
So, yeah, I think he was probably an
intelligence broker, but I believe he
was under the control of the Israelis.
How exactly does does this I mean, I
don't know how much you can go into
here, but how does the process of
attaining and utilizing an intelligence
asset like this work?
Uh we would we would need half a day to
talk about it, but
an access agent The Israelis are not
going to recruit Bill Clinton or Andrew
Mountbatten-Windsor.
So, they do the next best thing. They
recruit somebody who's close to those
people.
Like Jeffrey Epstein. And you give him
plenty of money,
and he buys this giant house on a
private island and he wires every single
room including the bathrooms for audio
and video.
And then you invite your friends to come
and have sex with children.
And to get them into compromising
positions.
You record everything that they say, you
report it back to your handlers and just
in case they object, well, you've got
this video putting them in these
compromising positions.
Do you think that this
leverage I suppose is another why
Western states are
so cautious to criticize Israel?
Probably not.
Okay. Um, I think really it's it's the
money in politics.
Mhm.
I think this was more of a purely
intelligence operation.
Okay. Okay. And I've heard talk as well
that he's got moderately strong links to
the CIA.
No. He He
No. He repeatedly volunteered
uh to work with the CIA. There's no
evidence that the CIA ever responded.
Uh and then a couple of years before his
death, he had his attorney reach out to
the CIA asking
uh through the Freedom of Information
Act
to um
to receive some kind of confirmation
that he had been trying to work with the
CIA.
And
there was no response to that either.
Okay, so there's no
evidence that he actually worked with
them or okay, interesting. And back to
um
I don't want to linger on this too long,
but back to the idea that he wasn't
murdered and that he indeed committed
suicide. I mean, there's lots of
conspiracy theories and these things um
in this area. What makes you
um certain that he was that he did
commit suicide.
Because I've served in prison,
I know what American prisons are like.
All the guards have their heads up their
asses, number one.
They're supposed to walk around every 15
minutes and make sure that everybody is
okay. They don't because they're in the
guard booth either sound asleep or
masturbating, looking at porn, or
surfing the internet, or on the phone
with their girlfriends.
So, they don't walk around. In the case
of Epstein, it was 2 hours before they
walked around rather than every 8
minutes.
The cameras never work.
There are cameras everywhere. They're
just not connected to anything.
So, people are like, "Oh my god, the
camera, there's this glitch." Yeah, the
cameras reset every 24 hours and they
tape over the previous 24 hours. So, the
handful of cameras that work actually
reset themselves.
Um
you're looking at a guy
who
was going to spend
the rest of his natural life in prison.
Period. It doesn't matter that he had
his own island or the widest townhouse
in Manhattan or a billion dollars or
fancy friends in important positions. He
was going to die on a steel prison bunk
after spending every day of the rest of
his life in prison.
Who would would rather be dead?
Mhm.
I suppose especially when he's come from
that the lifestyle that he was living
before with the wealth and the Exactly
right. Mhm. Okay. Okay, well, that's
interesting. I spoke with his brother
Mhm.
a couple of weeks ago.
Right after this stupid AI-generated
picture came out of him just walking
down the street in Tel Aviv with three
bodyguards.
And um you know, some of my my friends
in independent journalism
ran with this saying, "Oh my god, it's
the proof. He was He lived. He was He
escaped from the prison. It was a" No,
you morons. It's AI. It's obviously AI.
He's not just walking down the street.
So, I spoke with his brother. His
brother identified the body.
His brother accompanied the body to the
crematorium.
He's dead.
And we can have the argu- the argument
over whether or not he committed suicide
or or was murdered. I believe he
committed suicide.
But, uh,
but he's dead.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Well, I'll move on now
to
a very separate issue, which is, um,
your work for Russian media. I know
you've been criticized for this, um,
Only by one person.
Okay. Okay. Yes. Yes. Um, I must have
just seen that one person, then. Um,
Why why did you make the choice to go
into this area of work? I've heard you
say it was perhaps due to financial,
purely financial, reasons.
>> I I am a convicted national security
felon.
Okay?
If you're aware of some job that I could
have that would allow me to put my five
children through college, I'm all ears.
Mhm. But, part of the plan that was
enacted against me was to ruin me for
life.
And the only job that I could get
was to have a radio show that just
happened to be on a Russian network.
Now, it was written into my contract
that I could say anything I wanted
and criticize anybody I wanted,
including Vladimir Putin, which I did.
On the day that Russia invaded Ukraine,
I opened my show by saying, "I
unreservedly condemn the Russian
invasion of Ukraine, and I urge Russian
troops to withdraw immediately. Mhm.
Yeah, I wasn't attacking you for for
your
>> No, I I get it. But I and I'm asking
rhetorically. I'm not asking you
specifically. What's the problem?
Well, I think
>> knows you can't criticize Israel on
American in the American media.
Yes, you probably can't.
>> What's the What's the difference? Mhm.
Yes. Yeah, I I I think that
there's no evidence for Russian media
being
any more um
narrative-driven or focused on
disinformation than the UK media. And I
think that the attitude that the UK
media, for example, takes is probably
evidence that perhaps they're even more
biased. So.
Yeah.
Um okay, so
>> May I May I add one thing? Mhm. The
criticism that I worked for Russian
media came from Andrew Bustamante, a
very public former CIA officer, who runs
a website where he sells his training
from the CIA. He takes his training that
he underwent and he um
will teach you,
you know, CIA training.
Does he train Russians?
Chinese?
It's my understanding he'll train
anybody who pays.
So, what's the difference?
If I have a show on a Russian network or
he's training Russian intelligence
officers in CIA techniques,
what's he doing?
>> in that in fact sounds more problematic.
I would think so. Mhm.
Mhm.
Okay, well, um
I'll move on now to
a bit more of a um funny topic, I
suppose, which is Area 51.
And these sorts of conspiracy theories
that are surrounding these um
these sites. Do you think that there's
any legitimacy to any of this and the
the claims that the government are
hiding
very, very huge secrets from the
population.
Probably. I'm not sure that those
secrets are held at Area 51.
But yeah, I think there's
I think there's a lot of evidence out
there. On my first day at the CIA, I
asked my new boss, "So, where are the
aliens?"
And he laughed and he said, "That's
everybody's first question on their
first day." He said, "We We don't do
that kind of thing. That's all at the
Pentagon."
And now we've had, you know, leaks
recently from the Pentagon, leaks of
videos.
Um I I have a lot of friends who are
former fighter pilots, F-16, F-18, you
know, F-35.
And literally every one of them has seen
something. Some ship. Sometimes they're
coming out of the water, out of the
ocean.
Everybody has seen something that is
completely inexplicable.
So, I mean, there has to be something
out there.
And I suppose those people would
be most um
knowledgeable on
aircraft and these things, so it there's
some validity, I suppose, yeah. Right.
Okay. Right.
What do you think that the public
doesn't understand? What's the biggest
thing the public doesn't understand
about the CIA and these sorts of
organizations? The CIA's job is very,
very simple. The CIA's job is to recruit
spies, to steal secrets, and to analyze
those secrets so that
the policy maker can make the best
informed policy.
Um
counterterrorism, counterintelligence,
you know, yes, assassination squads,
yes, but not
space aliens and, you know, alien
technologies. There are offices at the
Pentagon where that's all they do.
Uh
it's not the CIA. Uh, the CIA is not
beaming waves at your head. The CIA is
not communicating with you through
the filling in your tooth.
The CIA doesn't give a about you
unless you have access to
classified foreign intelligence.
I think those are the probably the most
basic and most important things that
people should know about the CIA.
Okay. Okay. Well, I've got a few points
of reflection now if you don't mind um
My first question here would be, do you
regret joining the CIA in the first
place? No. Best job I ever had. Went to
72 countries, enjoyed every minute of
it. I regret that after 9/11 the CIA
became a criminal organization. But no,
I don't regret joining.
What was your favorite country that you
visited?
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> I
I have two answers. The The most My My
favorite country in terms of just
natural beauty
was Oman on the southeastern corner of
the Arabian Peninsula.
The most fascinating country I ever
visited
historically
uh, was Syria.
Because the the things that you look at
as you're going through the day are
mentioned in the Bible. They're so old.
I really I really loved both of those
places.
And what would you say your least
favorite or the most That's the most
dangerous would be a better question.
Country that you've been to as?
Oh, I've been to some really dangerous
places. I served in Pakistan. I went to
Somalia. I went to Yemen five times.
There are plenty of dangerous places out
there.
My least favorite place that I ever
served was India.
Um, Indians are mean to one another.
This caste system they have is just
awful. It's racist and
bigoted and just
it's just awful.
And I've never been to a place on Earth
as physically dirty
as uh
as India. And you just have to accept
the fact that you're going to get sick
there. There's nothing you can do to
protect yourself. Nothing. Just accept
it.
And then try to deal with it as best you
can once you get sick.
In terms of the few countries that you
mentioned being very dangerous, how
dangerous were these countries? Can you
Is there any way you could quantify it
for the viewers or Yeah, I I was twice
the victim of assassination attempts.
Um
I narrowly escaped car bombs twice.
Uh And one of those car bombs killed um
four dozen people and wounded hundreds.
So, yeah, I mean, there there are active
attempts to murder you every day.
>> [music]